Guide to the Butter Miners' Union No. 1 Records 1900-1967
Montana Historical Society Archives
Butter Miners' Union No. 1 Records
1900-1967
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-4774 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 208
Butte Miners' Union No. 1 (Butte, Mont.)
6 linear feet of shelf space
This collection consists of the records of the Butte Miners' Union No. 1 and containing incoming correspondence (1940); financial records (1934-1967), including membership dues and office accounting; a subject file (1956-1962) regarding the United Unions Recreation Council; and miscellany, including a list of members serving in the armed forces during World War I.
The Butte Miners' Union (BMU) was established in Butte, Montana, in March 1885, a result of the reorganization of the seven-year-old Butte Workingman's Union. The BMU fought for a minimum wage for miners and a closed shop. With chartered branch affiliates in Granite, Neihart, Castle, and Champion, BMU members took the lead in the establishment of the Western Federation of Miners in 1893.
Content Description:
Records. 1900-1901, 1934-1967. 6 linear feet. This collection consists of the records of the Butte Miners' Union, No. 1, and contains incoming correspondence (1940); financial records (1934-1967), composed for the most part of records of membership dues and office accounting; a subject file (1956-1962) on the Butte Miners' Union Youth Center/United Unions Recreation Council; and miscellany, including a list of members serving in the armed forces during World War I.
Arrangement:
by series
Acquisition Information:
available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Labor Unions--Miners; Mines and Mineral Resources--Montana--Butte; Butte (Mont.)--Industries--Mines and Mineral Resources; Mines and Mineral Resources; Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Incoming Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous (includes itemized list of expenses of the Community Peace Mobilization), 1940 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
- Financial Records
  - Cash account book, Jan.1959- Sept.1967 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Cash receipts and deposits, Jan.1936- Sept.1942 (Box-folder OVBX / 1)
  - Dues journal (includes member's name, card number, amount paid) [BOX #2 does not exist], Oct.1934- Jan.1936 (Box-folder 1 / 3-5)
  - Dues journal (includes member's name, card number, amount paid), Jan.-Sept. 1936 (Box-folder 3 / 1-2)
  - Dues journal (includes member's name, card number, amount paid), Sept.-Dec. 1936 (Volume Vol. 1-2)
  - Dues journal (includes member's name, card number, amount paid), Dec.1936- Oct. 1937 (Volume Vol. 3-6)
  - Dues journal (includes member's name, card number, amount paid), Oct. 1937- Nov. 1938 (Volume Vol. 7-9)
  - Dues journal (includes member's name, card number, amount paid), Nov. 1938- Feb. 1940 (Volume Vol. 10-12)
  - Dues journal (includes member's name, card number, amount paid), Feb.-Dec. 1940 (Volume Vol. 13-15)
  - Dues journal (includes member's name, card number, amount paid), June 1937- June 1939 (Volume Vol. 15-16)
  - Dues journal (includes members' name, card number, amount paid), Jan-Dec. 1940 (Volume Vol. 17-18)
  - Dues journal (includes members' name, card number, amount paid), Dec 1940- July 1941 (Volume Vol. 19-20)
  - Dues journal (includes members' name, card number, amount paid), July 1941- Mar.1942 (Volume Vol. 21)
  - Dues journal (includes member's name, card number, amount paid), Jan.-Oct. 1941 (Volume Vol. 22)
  - Dues journal (includes member's name, card number, amount paid), Oct.1941- July 1943 (Volume Vol. 23)
  - Dues journal (includes member's name, card number, amount paid), Jun.1946- Dec. 1950 (Volume Vol. 24)
  - Dues journal (includes member's name, card number, amount paid), Jan. 1951- Jan. 1954 (Volume Vol. 25)
  - Entertainment fund record, Jan. 1947- Jan. 1954 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
  - Drum and Bugle Corps fund record, Aug. 1943- May 1949 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
  - Expense ledgers (check dispusement by account), 1936-1941, Jan.1966- Oct.1967 (Box-folder OVBX / 1)
  - General fund record (includes hospital premium fund), Feb. 1942- Dec. 1949 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
  - General fund record, Jan.1956- Dec.1961 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - General ledger, 1936-1966 (Box-folder OVBX / 1)
  - Promissory notes, 1946 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
  - Receipts, 1946-1949, 1953 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
  - Record of original entry, Jan.1936- June 1967 (Box-folder OVBX / 1)
  - Sports and entertainment funds record, Mar. 1940- Feb. 1947 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
  - "Time Worked at Gagnon Mine", Oct. 1900- June 1901 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
  - Trustees' book of bills allowed (includes standing of accounts in general, entertainment, and legislative committee funds), Jan.-July 1936 (Box-folder 4 / 3)
  - Trustees' book of bills allowed (includes standing of accounts by funds), Aug. 1936- 1940 (Box-folder 4 / 4-8)
  - Trustees' book of bills allowed (includes standing of accounts by funds), 1941 (Box-folder 5 / 1)
  - Trustees' ledger, Oct.1941- Dec.1942 (Volume Vol. 26)
  - Trustees' financial report, Jan.11, 1942 (Box-folder 5 / 2)
  - Union dues assigned from Anaconda Copper Mining Company/The Anaconda Company (includes Boland Development Company, Ltd., 1961; and miscellaneous receipts, 1952-1953, 1961), June-Dec. 1949; June-Dec. 1961 (Box-folder 5 / 3)
- Printed Materials
  - "Miners Strike Bulletin", Apr.15, 1946 (Box-folder 5 / 4)
- Subject Files
  - Butte Miners' Union Youth Center / United Unions Recreation Council, 1956-1962 (Box-folder 5 / 5)
- Miscellany
  - "Itemized Account of Material in Office", Jan.3, 1935 (Box-folder 5 / 6)
  - List of miners who served in the armed forces during World War I [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: map case], n.d. (Box-folder OVFD /)
  - Membership roster (arranged alphabetically, includes name and card number. August 18, 1954 roster includes occupation, and "Members of Butte Miners' Union #1 in Good Standing on Weekly Payrolls"), Jan.17, 1948; Jan.21, Aug.18, 1954 (Box-folder OVBX / 2)
  - Membership roster "Butte Miners' Union No. 1 W.F.M." (arranged alphabetically), n.d. (Volume Vol. 27)
  - Membership roster (arranged alphabetically; includes name and card number) (Box-folder 5 / 7)
  - Poll books (includes name and card number; also includes "Excuse Book" re non-voting members), June (Box-folder 5 / 8)
  - Poll books, n.d. (Box-folder 5 / 9)
  - Strike duty record, Apr.1946 (Box-folder 5 / 10)
  - "War Labor Board Policy on Vacation Plans and Vacation Plans in Effect in the Non-Ferrous Metals Industry", 1944 (Box-folder 5 / 11)